hello and welcome it is June 3rd 2024
we're in active inference guest stream
82.2 with Robert Warden today we're
going to be discussing three-dimensional
spatial cognition bees and bats so thank
you Robert for joining again to you for
the presentation and looking forward to
it
thanks Dan okay well as Dan said I'm
talking about three-dimensional spatial
cognition in small animals particularly
like bees and bats for examples and what
I'm going to be doing is showing you a
demonstration program that does this and
so you can find the demonstration
program at this link at the bottom of
the picture and you can download it and
try it yourself or you can read a couple
of papers about this work which are
there on archive at that
address so so that is the the
introduction to get straight into it um
what this work represents I think is a
challenge for classical neuroscience and
by classical Neuroscience I mean the
assumption that all that happens in the
brain all cognition is done by neurons
connecting to each other by synapses and
so on and the challenge which I think
comes out of this work is that the main
result is that neurons are actually not
capable of that they cannot represent
three-dimensional space because they're
too imprecise and too slow so the
resulting challenge for Neuroscience is
to show this idea is wrong everybody
thinks it's wrong everybody thinks
neurons do everything so you have to
show it's wrong by building a working
model of neural computational model of
3D space and checking that it really
scales and can perform somewhat like
animals perform I think just writing
papers and talking about is not enough
you actually got to build a model and
show it
works and for building that model the FP
neural process model is the best
starting point I believe so that's where
this talk is going uh it gets there
by of 3D spatial cognition so what is
that spatial cognition I just first say
is a very important problem the primary
task of any animal brain is to control
its movements physical movements it
limbs in 3D and that's a 3D problem and
it has to do that at all times of the
day and for most animals most of their
brain is devoted to this problem and we
believe being basian that they do this
by building and using basian maximum
likelihood model of three
three-dimensional
space and I my previous live stream was
about the subject how animals build
models in general
but the particular 3D model of space
that's been important since the caman
era When Animals first started having
precise Spence sense data like good eyes
and capable Limbs and that there's been
huge and sustained selection pressure on
all animal species since then to do it
well and what we believe is that animals
do do it rather well for instance our
own conscious awareness of 3D space must
come from something going on in our
brains and that is a rather precise
model in our conscious awareness of 3D
space around us so that must be quite a
good model of space in our heads and
going from us to small insects even a
small insect can land very skillfully on
the room of a coffee cup or any other
surface so that's why I say modeling 3D
spatial cognition is the top priority
for
neuroscience and we may look at all
sorts of problem s in Neuroscience this
is the one this is the hard heart of the
problem the thing we really need to get
right so how do you do it how do animals
build a 3D model of the local space
around them and the immediate problem is
that most of their sense data in their
vision is two-dimensional so how do you
get from two-dimensional Vision to
three-dimensional model of space there
are some constraints and people
obviously think of stereopsis with two
eyes where you can tell the depth of
things or appropriate setion and touch
but those constraints only apply to
restricted regions of the space around
an animal so for the rest of it what I
believe animals do is they build a model
of the space around them by moving in
space and this is a form of active
inference if you like that you have to
move in order move in space to find out
about
space and this is based on a very strong
basian prob probability that as an
animal move most of the things around it
not do not move so the world is like a
big rigid moving body around the animal
so the animal can compute object
locations by what is called structure
from motion
sfm and when you build a computational
model of this is actually fairly simple
computation to do uh what you can do is
fairly simple 3D Matrix operations to
maximize the likelihood of an object
being in a certain position and that's
what this program does does but if
you're doing that shape from motion
structure from motion it requires a
short-term spatial memory a working
memory positions of things and that's
what this demonstration program
does so the demonstration
program B is have
Vision some limited but not very bad
resolution but to have e echolocation
instead
that gives them both the echo delay and
it gives them a Doppler shift and we'll
talk about that later so both of those
animals move fast among static objects
so this 3D shape from motion is an
applicable way of working out where the
objects are so the program we're going
to show you builds a 3D model of space
in three different
ways firstly it can build an optimal
basian shape from model model and that
is
uh what I call a Brute Force
calculation uh I've discussed this in my
previous live stream and it's very hard
for animals to do it's not the way we
think animals do it but the interesting
thing about it is it gives you the very
best possible Basin model based on the
sense data so that's the first way the
second way is by dynamical object
tracking where animal makes an estimate
of where each object is in three
dimensions and then it keeps updating
that estimate every time from every step
along the track it takes it updates that
estimate um from its sense data and the
third model is doing that same object
tracking but doing it in the presence of
neural memory noise I should say this
computational model is built at Mars
level David Mars level two that is it's
not a neural implementation but I have
made it so that you can add simulate
neural noise to it so if you want to see
this program after you've seen it
demonstrated download it from this web
address and you can quite simply unzip
it and start start it
running so uh I will now switch to
demonstrating this
program so I end the
show and there is the program that's
what it looks like and what you see is
three different windows left Center and
right the left hand window is going to
be a three-dimensional view of some
space in which a b or a bat is moving
the center view is always just health
information and it tries to tell you how
to use all these sliders and buttons and
controls and the the right hand view is
just various graphs and we'll see some
of those as we go along so what happens
when you press the start button is you
see some three-dimensional space and
inside it um there on the left hand side
is an animal this time a b and the
colored circles are objects randomly
spaced in that
space and so the the lines going from
the B to the objects are lines of sight
and this is a three-dimensional view so
you can rotate it see the three
dimensions and that's what happens when
you rotate it the objects
rotate and so there at the moment we've
got nothing about the be's internal
model of space we've only got actual
space itself shown in the view in order
to show the B's internal model of space
we press the Run button and I'll do this
and you can see what happens so as you
press run the B starts moving that's the
green line it gets new lines of sight
and from the new lines of sight it
estimates the positions of all those
objects so I'll restart and do that
again and what you'll see this time is
that the estimates of the positions
appear as small circles with arrow bars
so the arrow bars are the gray lines the
small circles are where the B thinks the
object is so you can see the building B
is building rather an accurate model of
where the objects are from its sense
data I'll restart again and this time
we'll step through it one step at a time
to see how the be's model of space
evolves with time so one step and you
can see in the very early steps we'll
rotate it a bit to see show what's going
on the B makes starts making really
quite good estimates of where the
objects are each little white circle is
quite close to the blue
circle but the estimates have error bars
and the error bars are in three
dimensions showing the uncertainty of
the location estimate in all those
Dimensions so it's those estimates of
position that enable the be to to move
where it wants to do suppose these are
flowers it can go to the flowers and get
pollen or whatever it wants to do now I
said the program computes three
different kinds of model and the three
MO is always doing this as you go
through the steps on the track and these
three models are a full basian model and
that's what we're showing at the moment
full basian we can switch to a tracking
model that's the object Dynamic tracking
and there if I switch that you can see
the arrow bars and the objects hardly
move at all they do move a little bit
but this is one result of the program
that doing that tracking model which is
simpler to do than the full basian model
gives you nearly the same uh estimates
and same error
bars and the third model it computes is
a tracking model with noise and I switch
to this
one and again it's not moving very much
actually uh but I'll I'll move it on a
bit and you'll see that noisy tracking
often is very different from um tracking
without noise so we're on tracking
without any noise at the moment we step
forward a
bit and the B keeps updating its
estimates of these positions as they go
and I now switch from tracking to noisy
tracking and you can see that noisy
tracking is significantly worse than
tracking they noisy estimates have
drifted away from the true positions of
the
object that is really the
second I've by the way I'm running this
with a fairly small level of neural
noise at the moment you can adjust the
level of neural noise you're can adjust
the bee's visual accurity adjust all
sorts of things using these sliders and
try running the program again this is
running with a fairly small level of
noise so I keep stepping
and the noisy tracking estimate keeps
getting worse but I go back to the
tracking estimate the tracking estimate
without neural noise is pretty much dead
on so I'll restart again and I'll run
again because then we can show the graph
at the end of the run which shows what's
happened to these
errors so if I run again
now you look at the ground on the right
and what that is doing is comparing
tracking which is the black curve versus
noisy tracking which is the red curve
and these are steps along the be's track
those the same steps we saw there but
these vertical axis is the level of
error in the depth that the B estimat
and you can see that tracking is rather
small errors it homes in on true
position of the object whereas with
memory noise you get much bigger errors
and in fact the errors are very
unpredictable if you
rerun um we just rerun it again you find
that the errors coming from noisy
tracking they do seem to vary quite a
lot from one run to the next noisy
tracking is pretty unpredictable
basically so there the errors have gone
right up and they've come down again
whereas ordinary tracking without noise
is nice convergence towards the true
positions so that is really the second
key result of the simulation that is
that a tracking model is a realistic
model of how animals estimate positions
of things around them but if you add
noise to it even adding a small amount
of noise completely messes up the
tracking model now there are more things
you can show with this model you can
show for instance how animals use their
model to detect what is moving around
them because obviously when an animal is
moving it is quite hard for it to detect
motion from its visual field because
when it's moving everything is moving in
its visual field so it has to use the
three-dimensional model to work out what
is actually moving and if you also plot
the efficiency of motion detection you
find that too is very much poorer when
you ad memory noise so I think I'll stop
at this point the program also does a
simulation of bats but I won't step
straight into that perhaps we could come
back to that at the end of the talk if
somebody wants to hear about it uh but
for the moment let's
just step back and find what we have
concluded from the bees model now where
is my
presentation um
now I've got to resume the presentation
some how do I do
that yeah you get back to the
presentation so the key points that I
think I may have shown you is that in
the 3D view you can see the track of the
animal you can see its lines of site you
can see sorry my phone is ringing sh it
up
I've shown you the three I've shown you
where the real objects are those are the
circles the colored circles shown you
the objects as located in the internal
model I've shown you shape for motion
I've shown you what the arrow bars are
and
you can rotate the 3D
view I've shown you the three different
models of 3D space the full basian model
the dynamic object tracking model and
the tracking model with memory
errors um as I say when you run this
program you can change all sorts of
parameters to see how it's sensitive to
the
parameters and um I've shown you the B
spatial model I've shown you how the
arrow bars are particularly the the
depth dimension
and I've shown you how memory noise
degrades the
model
so here are the key results that the
best possible model any animal could
build from its sensation is a very good
model and in fact it's more precise than
the sense data because if the animal can
assume that objects don't move then over
time an animal can build up a very good
understanding of where objects are
better than than its raw sense
data animals can't do any better than
that but dynamical object tracking works
pretty well it's almost as good as the
full basing
Mo and it only works if spatial memory
has very high precision and I didn't say
the levels of precision that I put into
the program which start to spoil the
tracking model they're about one part in
a
100 and that I believe is much more
precise than the most neural
representations of space can give so
that's the next part of this talk how do
we do that modeling with a neural model
of the brain the classical neural
model so how do you build a neural
spatial memory and this
is a changed quote from Animal Farm
where they said two legs bad four legs
good two Dimensions is easy three
dimensions is hard because two
Dimensions you can easily do a sheet of
neurons representing two Dimensions
whereas in three dimensions you don't
have that option and there are several
possible memory designs you can have a
two-dimensional sheet of neurons and you
can represent the third dimension by
depth depth by the third yeah you can
have some other variable representing
depth or you can have a
three-dimensional clump of neurons where
position in the clump represents a 3D
position or you can represent all three
dimensions of an object position by
neural firing rates
now none of these work well for object
tracking I think we can quite simply
eliminate the 3D Clump model but the
other two models have a problem with
neural error rates and if neural
information is encoded as firing rates
of
neurons typically you have a neuron
firing n times in some inter time
interval T and then the Precision with
which it can represent some real
quantity is of the order of one part in
square root of n now n / T is typically
five or between five and 50 pulses per
second on most animal
brains but for insects and small mammals
the time they've got to H have to update
their internal model of space is very
small typically less than a tenth of a
second so if the time is a tenth of a
second you get n less than 10 and that
gives you errors of the order of 30%
which are much bigger than the 1% errors
which I said are needed for
tracking uh structure from motion so the
conclusion of this is that the
neurons when they represent space
there's a tradeoff between speed and
precision faster you have the less
precise it is and this trade-off is just
too hard
so I believe there is no working neural
model of 3D spatial cognition now the
three the three points in blue I've said
before um they say spatial cognition is
very important and animals do it well
and we've had this problem for a long
time in his book Vision 40 years ago
David Mah identified the challenge and
he started work on it he defined what he
called a 2 and a half D sketch and
various other models now I believe that
in terms of building new neural models
of how spatial cognition Works people
have really not be moved Beyond
this why I think the main reason is that
the memory problem is just too hard that
memory gives them two big errors and is
too slow and I suspect that over the
years there been many people who look at
this problem and they decide to move on
and do something else instead but the
result is
that spatial cognition is the central
problem neuros science we don't have a
model of it and so this is rather like
theory of planetary motion without a Sun
or a theory of the atom with no
nucleus so how does this relate to
Active Vision I think Active Vision is
one way to explore this problem Active
Vision describes how 3D spatial model
can be inferred from vision and there
are quite a few papers on it they've
focused on very aspects of it they
focused on 2D scene classification they
focused on the tradeoffs between various
objectives like choice of visual sards
they focused on 3D robotics as far as I
know none of them have really focused on
how animal brains practically build a 3D
model and I believe that existing Active
Vision models do not address the issue
of neural error rates one reason for
this is that the standard activ INF
toolkit in matlb I believe it doesn't
model neural error rates it assumes I
believe an abstract perfect neuron with
very precise representation of
quantities and error rates are actually
not an issue for many of these
applications they're not an issue for
Robotics and they're not an issue really
for making discrete
choices but as I've said in this talk so
far the accuracy of 3D model really
matters and neural error rates are the
big
problem if we set that problem on S one
side for a moment there is the in issue
of active inference tradeoffs and there
are many many interesting tradeoffs you
can examine in Active
Vision and the key tradeoff I believe is
one between freezing and
moving as I've shown in the
demonstration animal has to move by has
to move in order to infer the 3D
positions of things around it by shape
from motion it also of course has to
move to achieve practical goals like
feeding and fleeing and meting and so on
on the other hand it can freeze and
freezing it may conserve energy it may
be able to detect what's moving simply
directly from its visual field which is
much easier and it may itself avoid
detection so these are very key
tradeoffs they're absolutely essential
for Lifetime Fitness for many animals
animals have to make this tradeoff or
these tradeoffs any moment of the day
and so we've got plenty of empirical
data about it and I think it'll be a
very useful area to explore
explore now I'm going to switch to
something completely different having
said that neural storage of spatial
positions is a very hard problem I'm
going to talk about an
alternative possible alternative way of
storing spatial data
and so we if you assume that there's a
round some round region inside the brain
of a fairly large diameter D and this
holds waves with a minimum wave length
which I call Lambda and that neurons can
couple to the waves both as transmitters
and receivers and the wave can persist
at least for fractions of a second so
the wave can act as a working memory for
positions
and the number of object positions you
can store in the wave can be up to D
over Lambda Cube and that's a can be a
very large number the spatial Precision
which one object position is stored can
be one part in D over Lambda and I think
that D over Lambda can be very large so
you can easily get Precision better than
one part in 100 is what you need to
build the spatial model so in summary
wave storage of 3D position may have a
lot of computational benefits it can
give a natural fit to the
problem it can give High precision and
high capability it can give you very
fast response times low spatial
Distortion and some other benefits which
are described in the
papers so apart from its computational
benefits is there any evidence for wave
storage in the
brain I believe there are two quite
powerful lines of evidence one of which
comes from the insect central body the
central body of the insect brain is a
very small part of the brain in the
middle of it and it consists of a
fan-shaped body and the elliptical body
and it has this shape which is
remarkably well conserved across all
insect species and there's an insect
brain database and I've gone to the
insect brain database and pulled from it
the shapes of the central body from a
few typical insect species and here you
can see the fan shaped body and the
ellip iCal body and it's very constant
across all kinds of insects and you can
see it's approximately a round shape so
it's well suited to hold the
three-dimensional
wave and it does multisensory
integration and so it's quite likely
quite probable that it holds spatial
positions and insects have very few
neurons in their brain to do it in any
other
way and what I think is significant is
how constant round the insect central
body is compared with all the other
parts of the insect
brain so that's one piece of evidence
from the insect central body the other
piece of evidence comes from the
mamalian
thalamus as you may know the eamus of
most mammals all mammals is
approximately spherical and it's
connected to all sense data and all
cortical re
regions but the important thing is that
the shape of the th
is highly conserved across all
species and there's an important aspect
of the thalamus
Anatomy that unless you assume a wave
really doesn't make
sense uh because the thalamus consists
of a number of independent nuclei like
the pulvinar and the lgn and so on and
so forth and the connections across
within the thalamus between these
nuclei are very weak or even
non-existent so you could have this
picture here that the th where's my
pointer here's my pointer the thalamic
nuclei which white circles here they all
connect in two ways to the cortex but
they don't connect to each other so one
thalamic nucleus here could easily start
moving out towards the cortex and the
the distance the length of its axons
could decre
incase and its other connections it
doesn't need other connections so all
the nuclei could migrate outwards
towards the cortex and you could still
have the same neural
synaptic
connectivity and the
same uh computational capability if
neurons only comput by synaptic
computation so this way you could save a
lot of energy in shorter axon length
so in summary it compack Thalamus only
makes sense if all the nuclei need to be
immersed in the same wave
so we now have three pieces of evidence
for a wave in the brain firstly there's
the computational Neuroscience that it's
a very difficult problem to build a 3D
model without it but you can build a 3D
spatial mod if you assume there's a wave
storing
positions secondly the insect central
body
is nearly round in all insects very well
suited to hold a wave and it appears to
be in the right part of the brain to do
that and thirdly the mamalian thalamus
which again has this round shape very
well suited to hold a wave and the
important thing here is that without a
wave the anatomy of the thalamus doesn't
make
sense so I would like you if you
remember only one thing about this talk
remember this slide there is quite a lot
of evidence for a wave in the
brain one thing I will say um is that
the wave is probably not an
electromagnetic wave because there's
quite a lot of interest in
electromagnetic fields in the wave from
researchers like Miller and mcfaden and
so on but an electromagnetic field can't
play the role that this wave is supposed
to is needed to play in other words the
key thing that this the wave is supposed
to do in this model is to store
information for fractions of a
second but an electromagnetic field in
the wave and there certainly are in the
m in the brain there certainly are
electromagnetic fields in the brain they
cannot store information for fractions
of a second and they cannot represent 3D
space like a
HRA and just to say a little more about
this if there's an electromagnetic wave
in the brain it has to obey Max's
equation so the wavelength times the
frequency is equal the speed of light
Lambda f equals
c and that means that 40 HZ typical
frequencies of these waves the
wavelength is 8,000 kilometers as large
as half the Earth so it's the conclusion
is that at 40
htz electromagnetic field is not a wave
it's a static field and it's driven
entirely by neuron firing so it doesn't
store the information so in summary
we're looking for something not electrom
magnetic and possibly some quanti
excitation something a bit exotic um in
the field of quantum biology I think we
shouldn't despair here because we know
evolution is a lot smarter than we are
at discovering these things and
explosing
them so here are some take-home
questions does 3D spatial cognition use
a wave in the brain in other words in
the light of the evidence I've shown you
what is the basing probability of that
hypothesis being true now I say these
take-home questions because I didn't
expect you to have an answer immediately
but perhaps you'd like to look at the
papers and see what the evidence is and
try and assess it in your own mind or do
you know some slam D killer reason why
they can't be a wave in the brain if you
do know reason what is that reason and
how do brains compute space how do
neurons on their own represent 3D space
with enough
Precision on on the other hand if there
might be a wave in the brain wouldn't
that be a a rather exciting and
revolutionary development it would
actually change the whole neuroscience
and it could address this Central
unsolved problem of how spatial
cognition takes place so I believe that
possibility should be explored
particularly for young researchers is
attractive it's Green Field research
it's not a well trodden path of
classical
Neuroscience the classical Neuroscience
model of molic pits neurons and heav
heian synapses that's 75 years old now
so I would like to encourage people to
get out and
explore or
again come back to the earlier slide
here a crisis in
Neuroscience the result of this work I
think is that neurons can't represent 3D
space because they're too imprecise and
too slow so the crisis is can you show
this is wrong can you show it by
building a working neural computational
model and checking its scales
properly so the FP neural process model
is the starting point for that I think
it's a good problem to work on because
it is a crisis and big Cris big advances
in science tend to come out of
crises so what I'm advocating and this
is my last slide is a twin track
research program to build two different
Active Vision models of 3D spatial
cognition one is a pure neural model
which is a classic Fe neural process
model can this be made to work or are
the neural memory errors going to kill
it and secondly to try to build a hybrid
wav neural
model and when you're building those
models we can explore the tradeoffs that
active inference is so good at at
Computing and particularly the trade-off
between freezing and moving so there are
a couple of candidate projects for of
the active inference
Institute okay that's
it awesome thank you
Robert I have some questions and some
people have asked questions in the live
chat so I'll uh I'll ask them so first
just while I'm recro everything how
would you connect this to the
requirements equation earlier work
because you mentioned that there was
a requirements equation driven
calibration of the optimal navigation so
what does that look like to have the
optimal navigation according to the
requirements
equation well uh to summarize on the
requirement
equation you can model how brains evolve
and this is the previous live stream and
you can show that they evolve towards
making a purely basian calc calculation
of their best model of the world from
the sense data but
that purely basian calculation is rather
expensive and it's been well known in Fe
that full basian calculations is
intractable for most animals and so that
is a very expensive
calculation and it's probably not the
way animals do it but it it is it can be
done on digital computers and it can be
done in this model I've showed you and
the first model the full basian model is
actually Computing the requirement
equation from the bees or the bats sense
data the second model a tracking model
is a is an approximation to that which
is a lot cheaper but seems to give very
nearly the same
results okay
awesome let us dive into a few mammal
and insect neuroanatomy questions so
I'll start with a set of questions from
the the live chat this is going to be
about mammal
neuroanatomy okay Tim Ritter asks do you
assume this wave property for all
thalamic nuclei primary and secondary or
for specific ones EG pulvinar or
mediodorsal very good question I don't
know the answer I mean at this stage I
believe the whole phalus is around
spherical near spherical volume with the
wave going through all of it so they are
all immersed in that same wave so even
the pulvinar the pulvinar certainly is
even the lgn which is rather small and
is a pass through nucleus I think they
all are so I
think for instance I think um people
always say the thalamus is a relay uh
sense data gets the cortex by Thalamus
but people don't have a very good reason
why it has to go through these relays
nuclear in order to get there I think
it's doing something about locating
about I think the wave has some
involvement there but this is very early
days I don't know the answer tool okay
another question from Tim on mamalian
neuroanatomy what about 2D orientation
would you expect similar waves in hippoc
cample instead of thalamic regions or is
2D sufficiently easy to get by
without yeah basically I believe 2D is
easy enough to get by and the
hippocampus is by no means suitable to
hold a wave they have all sorts
hippocampi have all sorts of different
shapes
so yes I think that was a Core theme
between the mammal and insect areas is
the conserved shape and then also the
allometric differences over Evolution
where the size differential of the
insect central body changes much less
than other primary sensory regions and
that was in your paper yeah that's right
yeah and that kind of implies that that
small size of the central body it's only
a few percent of the whole insect brain
seems to be
enough yeah and that the properties
which it hosts or enables might be
related to its physical extent or like
to its surface area to volume
ratio and not a function like for
example in the uh antennal lobe where
the old factory information are coming
in there are these little glami and
different species have from several tens
to several hundred of these olfactory
glami like ants have many and they have
more old factory re ctors in their
genome and they have more uh old factory
glami in that region or insects with
more compound eye sections they have
larger optic loes so the primary sensory
regions have very
large variation amongst species but then
as you get into the central
body uh you get much more conserved
anatomy in size and then the mushroom
body on the top part of the brain is
something a little bit in between that
might have more of an analogy to like
Maman cortex where there actually is the
possibility to scale its cognitive
capacities through size changes because
it has some kind of like repetitive or
stereotyped
layout yeah I mean there are a load of
fascinating questions in neuroanatomy
which relate to this and and if you
pursue the this hypothesis
then there's all those interesting
questions I'm not an expert on insect or
main neuron Anatomy but there's a load
of interesting questions in
there cool so um about the
be spatial cognition so we know that
bees use a variety of visual cues
ranging from the
landmark and the landscape recognition
to polarization of light and so on and
also as you pointed out the central body
does multisensory
integration so how do we think about the
possibly complimentary or redundant
information provided by these different
aspects of the visual fields and what
does your simulation focus in
on well I mean I believe that what the
central body and the thalamus both do is
multisensory integration in other words
animals should they they need to make
the best 3D model of space they can and
they need to use all their sensat to use
it apart from possibly smell that's an
interesting question uh and so both of
them do multicenter integration and
ideally one would put in the simulation
one would have things like stereopsis
one would have object recognition one
would have light polarization all sorts
of
sources this program only does simple
Vision or simple echolocation at the
moment but it should do all multi-entry
integration in in a single basian
maximum likelihood model of the
whole um all sense data coming in at the
moment interesting yeah with sound or
with smells it it would be interesting
to see how those come into play and and
how do you think about in in the
simulations presented here
egocentric and allocentric
navigation because you mentioned how the
kind of simplifying assumption is that
the world is a rigid fixed body so you
can have these kind of Duality where
like I'm moving and the world is fixed
and then there's sort of like I'm fixed
and the world is moving so how does that
relate to that question to to that
egocentric allocentric distinction yeah
very good question I mean I
think the frame of ref used for the
model should be as much allocentric as
it can be because the wave has to
persist and if the wave just persists it
represents an object at a constant
position so you want to have a frame of
reference where most objects are at
constant
positions so I think that makes
allocentric but obviously has to change
from time to time every few seconds it
has to
switch because it can't just stay
allocentric
H interesting so now to connect that to
what you brought up about move or stay
that kind of fundamental uh animal or
fundamental mobile
organismal nervous system question I
thought about different body plans where
the eyes or the visual component are
unable to move separately from the body
like a bee can turn its body but it it
can't rotate its eyes whereas in humans
for example we have optic Cade so
they're that stay or
move yes we have turning our posture and
moving through space but also we see
like this
microcosm where when the Gaze is fixed
there's High precision and then movement
in the world is associated with movement
of objects and then whereas when a iade
is dispatched during the Cade our visual
attention is
alleviated and then it's because during
that time all the movement of pixels
essentially is ascribed to the movement
of the eye so we see kind of like a
microcosm of the two modes of movement
and stability in motion detection in the
cating but for other organ organisms
that don't have isoc the only way that
they can get that kind of alternating
movement and stability is by moving
their
body yeah yeah I mean I always think of
isad as particularly Predators if you
like that want some high resolution in
some direct some particular direction
whereas for most insects as you say that
there is not the option of a high
resolution phobia um but I think of
Cades as being cheap
there's I mean the freeze move tradeoff
is a real tradeoff that if an animal
moves it can be detected as moving and
it can't detect motion itself as well as
if it's stationary so that's a real hard
trade-off an animal has to make whereas
Cades you can make them cheaply when
whenever you
like yes
yes and also it's really interesting
like how often the Behavioral Studies
just look at the direction of movement
but there's this whole timing of
movement and so there's definitely a lot
of empirical studies about whether fear
based movement like in a predator prey
uh or different kinds of movement
choices um where would you say attention
comes into play in the sense that the be
or the bat was just kind of taking it
all in it didn't have like some
restricted scope so it's kind of like a
uniform attention across objects and
across space and time but then we know
that we do have this visual attention
phenomena well yeah attention is very
important and uh I
think naively it's a search line model
of attention in other
words the wave representation of all
space represents all the space around an
animal but the animal can focus
attention on a region of the space and
what that's doing is tuning The
receptors in the thalamus so they are
sensitive to wave vectors in a certain
region so there's a whole load of issues
there about how the wave works as
whether it can how signals are rooted
from sensor inputs to specialist regions
of the cortex and I think atten is that
rooting of
information so again loads of big
questions
there yes with the wave I was kind of
thinking about the insect brain visual
input flowing in and also other
potentially inputs and all of these are
crashing on the shores of the central
body and then there's this kind of
stabilized dynamical wave
representation such that information
coming in differently changes the the
the sh the resting shape of the
wave and then that opens up like you're
now suggesting recurrent connections or
or other connections into that wave
hosting
region recurrent connections can modify
the shape of the wave attentionally and
then also the oh yeah the resting shape
of the wave can route or augment or
suppress other sensory information
coming in that'd be like water kind of
dumping to where there's already a high
water Point versus water going to where
there's low water yeah yeah Ian I think
key role of the wave is to persist a
background model of all 3D
space and then against that background
model you Center information that comes
in particularly
movement uh is best evaluated a piece of
new sense data you evaluate it much
better if you can compare and contrast
it with what you had before and that is
attenion and it it's it's the thalamus
if you like telling the cortex here pay
attention to here here's your old
information from this place in space
Here's your new information so tell me
what's
changed well this connection with frame
differencing
is very powerful predictive processing
predictive coding algorithms were built
by computer scientists and and
compression Engineers looking to make
video compression work and doing the
frame differencing because that's the
optimal way to compress video and then
that got brought also back into
Neuroscience where there's a lot of
focus on things like Edge detection and
these other 2D visual phenomena and then
as you're pointing to there's this kind
kind of Sun at the solar systems center
that's not really being discussed which
is like okay yes we have neurons in
different uh visual regions that are
excitable by vertical lines by diagonal
lines and so on but this is all flat
phenomena and the question of not just
shape
recognition but the question that's most
approximately relevant for movement and
the fitness related decisions for the
organism in the niche has to do with
its spatial
navigation not its like eyesight at the
eye
doctor
yeah not only spatial navigation how it
moves its limbs you know how where it
puts itot its foot next that sort of
thing and the 3D model I think does all
of that
okay I'll read a question from the live
chat how might the Cade relate to a
matrix of inputs versus a human-based
visual system movement on The Matrix may
give different spatial
Dynamics uh I'm not sure what we mean by
a matrix of inputs there but um as you
said during a cc visual input is kind of
blocked while the I is getting from A to
B uh whereas the wave persists and the
3D spatial model stays
constant and after a cade the eye has to
update the 3D spatial model in some
different place so
um I'm not I don't think I've answered
the question but perhaps
you what do you understand by
matrix it's what you
enter um
it's making me think about the
experiments where the for example the
fruit fly is placed on a a pingpong ball
in a harness in a virtual reality
setting so it's getting custom visual
input and its movements on the pingpong
ball just kind of Scrolls the ball so
it's basically fixed but it gives a lot
of degrees of experimental Freedom
around the
the um orienting of the body and what
visual inputs it gets so I wonder if
anywhere there we know about the the
time the time scale
of spatial orientation
updating because that would be very
critical to understand the nature of the
wave whe if it was something that was um
for example closer to the diffusion
rate of
ions then we might be looking more
towards like a Channel or pore based
hypothesis if it was something that was
faster than neural signaling it would
suggest something more like the direct
coupling or other kinds of of action so
what what makes you feel as you
suggested that it is not an
electromagnetic
stabilized wave
Fields well as I say the physic I mean
for electromagnetic wave we do
understand the physics and the
electromagnetic waves that measured by
EEG for instance they are a purely
passive consequence of neural activity
they don't persist in the information
for any time at
all whereas this wave I'm talking about
has to persist information
for fractions of a second so this
constant spatial model is kept persisted
while the Cades go on while the animal
moves well it computes shape from motion
so a pure electric field we we know the
physics is maxos equations and it does
not store energy store
information so it's purely a passive
reflection of what's going on the
neurons it's not a
memory h
so the neurons are especially if we
think about the several like thousand to
tens of thousand let's say in the insect
central body there's too few and they're
too sparse and noisy to in a purely
connectionist
neural uh framework to support the kinds
of empirical results that we see on the
other hand a purely field-based approach
has some issues that you just laid out
so it's it's very interesting that to at
least of the well-known mechanisms the
local field potential and the firing
rate rate coding type models that both
of them seem to have some
limitations and yet there's very strong
anatomical evidence for the functional
role of that region
oh yeah it's absolutely vital
region but I believe that just looking
at electric fields and magnetic fields
in the brain is not going to give you
memory and that's the key thing that I
think is needed to do structure from
motion you've got to have short-term
working memory to hold a little model of
space for a fraction of a
second do you see that as a kind of
special type of short-term memory or do
you think this is
the same memory
pool that like short-term audio memory
gets entered
into oh it's it's special it's different
from that yeah
definitely say it starts from how do you
how do you compete a 3D space
model how do you do structure promotion
you need short-term working memory for
for that purpose
specifically
interesting um the kind that enables us
to check for difference in v in visually
changing systems or what what does this
VIs visual working
memory
have well
basically it's it's not Vision because
it's
3D and uh checking for difference in the
visual
field is you can do it quicker you can
look directly at the visual field
whereas this model I think the 3D model
it's um it's maintained by a loop
between in in mammals between the
thalamus and and the cortex and it's a
40 htz cycle that maintains it so it
takes time to build the 3D
model and it's a bit slower than direct
visual change
detection interesting it's this tension
with like visual being what is
seen versus kind of a broader
imagine with the imagination of vision
um what about action in your model so
how were the paths
set yeah I said that the model was a bit
like active inference in the animal has
to move in order to understand space but
it's not really the program has not
modeled the kind of active inference
choices of how should I move to get the
best understanding of space and you
could do that you could make the be
choose this tragectory to get the best
on understanding of where the flowers
are or you you make the B choose it
tragectory for all sort those are the
active inference tradeoffs that the
program has not yet looked at and and
which can be looked at and I think are
very interesting that's awesome yeah
it's almost like the be in this
situation it's like on a train trying to
reduce its uncertainty about the
location of landmarks but it's just on a
it's on a rail it doesn't have policy
decision whereas once we start to close
that Loop and ask which direction of
movement or none given the costs would
reduce uncertainty about resolving this
kind of spatial
relationship then that that's where the
perception action start to like come
into play in benefit of each other and
potentially there's several Choice
successive moves can greatly reduce
uncertainty through otive sampling just
as we see ining and all other
situations and that would be like a
heris or strategy that that really does
work yeah I mean and another example
that I use somewhere is I believe that
predatory birds like Hawks when they're
approaching their target they don't go
in a straight line they move on a curve
to reduce the
uncertainty so that they continue to get
uh more information continue to see the
range of of of the
target if they just went straight for
the Target they wouldn't get a range fix
on
it
h now what about the difference between
the B and the bat whereas a b is simply
receiving the reflected photons let's
just say the b
is sending
out a invisible signal so how is this
kind of radar echolocation setting
similar and different to the vision
setting oh it's it's very different I
could show you that with the program if
you like
um what happens with the bat is from the
delay of an for a particular insect that
the bat is tracking from the delay of
the echo it sees the range to the insect
so it gets the insect constrained on a
sphere in its 3D model then from the
Doppler shift it actually sees the
perceives the cosine of the angle
between its directional movement and the
direction of the insect so what it gets
there is it constrains the sphere
surface of a sphere down to one Circle
in space so what the Bat gets is a
series of circles in space which
constrain the position of the insects
and I could show that on the program if
you like
sure okay um well how do I do that how
do I share again
yeah I'm Cur is the circle something
like is it like a hoop that you could
throw a basketball through or is it well
I I'll show
you um now I can't get rid of this
something on my screen it's the problem
um I've got a big black screen with a
two on it and I can't get rid of
it end show SP end show right
now am I sharing my screen or not not
yet um now how do I find where do that
how do I find where I am in
space
yeah that's an interesting question also
how these mechanisms Google window
somewhere the zoom window somewhere and
oh ZM that'll be
it how are these mechanisms repurposed
for digital
navigation semantic
navigation narrative
navigation uh just a minute let me find
oh God get away oh share screen tube
share okay right you got that we're back
okay so what we do is we change from B
to
bat and we start
again so what you have now is the bat
and several insects which are colored
circles here and what the bat has is its
echol location take the blue insect it's
EOL location constrains it to a sphere
in space and that's the delay of the
echo location and the Doppler shift
constrains the sphere down to a circle
so if we rotate these circles you see
that blue insect is on a circle from one
point in the bat's trajectory so as the
bat moves it gets successive circles for
the same insect so what we have is the
bat is moving and all these circles
highly
confusing and it gradually locates all
the insect better and
better but what if I restart and step
again if I
step I've
restarted right now if I
step what I can do is focus on one
insect if I focus on that insect then I
only see the circles from echolocation
of that one insect and I can step again
and get a new circle from the new step
and all the time the bat is optimizing
the position of that insect to get the
best fit to all the circles it has for
that insect so it's very different from
Vision but it can build a very good 3D
model from its
echolocation okay so to kind of confirm
what's happening here
there's there's for a given snapshot
ping with the sonar what is returned is
a circle of equip probable locations
that are kind of like the maximum
likelihood Ridge that constrains these
really s of Gan gussian Donuts if you
like okay
likelihood and then success of pings
enable you to look at the intersection
point of the circles to find out through
successive approximation the likeliest
location so this is what's Happening
Here on that light blue insect he's got
these three circles and that's the most
likely they're not very well
intersecting but that's the most likely
intersection Point that's if I go on
this back it's it's like a gaussian
mixture model you have those three Peaks
and then when you summate those three
Peaks that the the point that
interpolates them or just is the the
geometric average is the single maximum
likelihood estimate Point that's exactly
it yeah and again with the bat I can go
from Full basian model which is this
one full basian tracking or tracking
with noise and again the noise tends to
have nasty
effect where I look back at this one
here that's that dark blue
insect and I can rotate to see how the
circles go
so how is this how is this similar or
different than for example radar
navigation algorithms for planes or
ships I think it's quite
similar I
think yeah I mean they are making
maximum likelihood inferences from radar
signal and have you with this software
looked at the
computational like the runtime
complexity or the resource use
associated with scaling the number of
insects or scaling the resolution of
vision yeah you can scale the number of
insects for in if I scale up here the 30
insects I can run the model with 30
insect and
um
it's it runs perfectly
well so the model is quite efficient
because what it has to do for each
object um and for each time step it
simply has to do this Gan optimization
which turns out to be just a 3D Matrix
operation three three matrices and
that's very quick to
do and the so that's one of the
advantages of it that if animals are
trying to track a load of things around
them which they probably are it's quite
a quick efficient
computation but this is not the neural
implementation the problem is going from
here this Mars level two computational
model to a neural implementation and
that is where I think all the
interesting problems Li at least you
have this level two model as a kind of
starting point and the Basin model would
be trying to implement that in neurons
yes makes sense this is kind of the as
if
basian
algorithmic
map and the question is what proximate
mechanisms are capable of doing
these algorithms
functionally and neuroanatomy has
basically
localized to the region in mammals and
in in
vertebrates and so now we're in a space
of winnowing possibilities and leaving
the door open for unconventional
opportunities for how those regions
actually do it it's a very targeted
specific
agenda that that connects a first
principal grounding about how well the
navigation can proceed with the
requirements
equation On Through To to the
empirical patterns that we see those
empirical patterns might have some like
behavioral experiments well sometimes
can be hard to interpret as well though
for example there's a common experiment
where a wall that's shaped like an L is
set up and then people will use it to
test if an animal will go on the
hypotenuse to reduce the travel distance
or whether it will take the the around
the wall
however even if there was a
conceptualization of the ability to move
in the hypotenuse Direction an animal
might like prefer to move along
walls so then by the time you get to the
real animals
movements it's very tied up with not
just trying to be the optimal Landmark
resolving visual algorithm it's actually
engaging all these other
drives that can make it look like it's
lower efficiency or even like
supernaturally efficient on a given
domain yeah I I think there's all sorts
of animal experiments one could do but
interpreting them is not easy but
basically if you're looking in these
experiments to to to measure how good
the animal's internal 3D model is I
would like to with insects for instance
how good is that movement detection if
it's movement in depth that needs the 3D
model to resolve it rather than just the
V visual
field that's very interesting especially
in insects potentially where there's
little overlap between their two
compound
eyes
yeah yes um okay I'll read a question
from the chat as we kind of head towards
the
end use equal wrote how would perception
of ability to conceive of other domains
of time as a cognitive function change
spatial
awareness
um other dimensions of time I'm not sure
I understand that question other domains
of time domains what's other domains of
time
um well this is all a very
shortterm question it's fractions of a
second and time outside that interval
just doesn't come into it at all
really does that answer the question
you it might I think it might also be
pointing to our awareness of how we
handle our perception of time and
space and what does that open up or
enable for example for our perception of
space if we have a different perception
or conception of
time well that is a very deep question I
mean I think our perception of
chronological time long-term time is
something completely different from more
anything else in the animal kingdom I
think most animals live in the moment
really they're aware of what's happening
right now and what they got to do right
now and the rest just doesn't
matter whereas we exit what matters in
the moments to ruminate and
speculate yeah
absolutely um well what
other directions or or ways are you
hoping to take this
work well one way that is particularly
important I think although particularly
problematic is theories of
Consciousness in other other words
Consciousness most of our Consciousness
at any moment is consciousness of the
space around us and it seems to come
from our internal basian model of space
around us so this work is very related
to why we are conscious and there's
another paper and I'd like to give
another live stream just on that subject
because I think this gives a way forward
to a theory of Consciousness that can be
in many ways more satisfactory than we
get from purely classical neurom models
of the
brain that's awesome I'm also personally
very excited on the empirical insect
neuroanatomy side to look oh there are a
huge number of ways of look going
forward and insects are particularly
productive because you know they've got
to do it with a really small number of
neurons so it's really there's a lot of
experimental work on insects that can
illuminate this question yeah
absolutely cool yes the brains are fun
to dissect you can see it transparently
all there
and no backstage there um and then also
this on on the more transferable outside
of anology I think the octave
inference Loop closure with policy
selection of movements including stay go
noo decisions and which way to go and
then understanding how like well here's
the trajectory that would have been the
most Information Gain on resolving this
location um here's the trajectory that
maximized safety it's not moving or
something and then here's the trajectory
that that would have um done some other
thing then being able to look at
realized empirical
trajectories and then break those down
or look at their component loading
according to safety visual Information
Gain other kinds of heris or or impulses
to understand moments or kind of
fragments of trajectories like something
looks to briefly resolve its uncertainty
and then it doesn't need then the the
overall demand to resolve uncertainty
drops again and then it continues just
with inertia and then maybe that's a
very simple decision to make and then
there's probably all kinds of
cool patterns and ways to go yeah
there's a huge amount to
investigate another another topic by the
way is we've looked at mammals we've
looked at insects right at the opposite
ends of the spectrum there's a whole
load of stuff in between I think octopus
and squid are particularly interesting
but there's all the other species one
can look at say how do they do
space they have unique bodies and
different bodies but there's also
bringing in there the question of
underwater or space or fluid
media and then that and a bat flies but
it has the mamalian neuroanatomy so then
there could be like bird neuroanatomy
with its slight differences from the
mammal then there could be this question
of underwater and maybe there's some
mammals that have underwater navigation
maybe Dolphins would be like
bats but in
another fluid
media I hope people download the dotzip
and play
around so do
I any last comments
uh not really no I think I said it all
thank you thank you Robert well I I
greatly enjoying learning about the work
and seeing about how the
requirements
equation
Scopes a given problem setting and kind
of puts a meter stick on whatever the
inferential problem is inference plus
action problem is and then from there
the mar the
Marian research program is just kind of
laid out you can pursue it from the
mechanistic or from the algorithmic
elements but they all are connected
through on one hand in theory the
requirements equation and on the other
hand the empirical results that we
actually see
yeah cool so thank you again um I I come
back to the Fineman quote Richard
Fineman on his Blackboard it said if you
can't build it you don't understand it
this is all about building
it we can't build a
bug not
yet um thank you Robert see you for DOT
three see you bye for